DANIEL BERNIER

danbernier@gmail.com | danbernier.com

OVERVIEW

I'm a software engineer who values healthy teams, diverse perspectives, and legible systems. Whether it's prose or code, clear writing is worth the effort. I'm comfortable both teaching and learning, and I'm looking for a team with intellectual humility where people enjoy working together. I'm motivated most by the impact I have on the world and the people I meet.

Relevant Skills

Bridging between stakeholders and engineers. Mentoring, pair programming, agile methods. Distributed teams since 2013. Safely reviving legacy systems and untested codebases. Architecture, (micro)services, APIs. Automated testing. Ruby, Rails, GraphQL. Postgresql, MySQL, MongoDB. Generative art. Past: JavaScript, HTML, CSS. C#, Java, SQL Server, XML. Functional programming.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Staff Engineer at Continuity, September 2021 - present, acquired by Mitratech December 2021

While Continuity's place in Mitratech's plans for their acquisitions is being worked out, I'm winterizing the application: paying down technical debt, deleting dead code, streamlining outdated flexibilities. The platform's dependencies are all current, and the plan is for junior engineers to keep it that way until new leadership is found.

Senior Engineer at Smile Identity, April 2021 - September 2021

Senior Backend Engineer at TED Conferences, January 2017 - March 2021

As the only backend engineer for ted.com, I inherited a codebase that was brittle and disorganized. In the midst of shipping features and responding to rapid priority shifts, I worked incrementally to make it robust, performant, and maintainable; now, bugs are regularly caught before they're released. I arranged much of the codebase so non-technical teammates can safely change some of the content and behavior through code commits, and with the rest of the engineers I worked to evolve the interoperation of the systems to meet TED's changing needs.

Senior Software Engineer at Continuity, November 2013 - December 2016

While working on Continuity Control, an application for banks and credit unions to stay in

compliance with federal regulations, I helped grow the team to ten developers. We pair-programmed and mentored junior developers on software design and testing, architecture, project management, and agile methods. We shipped features consistently, made the application more performant and maintainable, and contributed to open source projects we used.

Developer at SeeClickFix, September 2011 - November 2013

I joined a start-up team looking to mature, and introduced them to agile, pair programming, and object-oriented design. Together, we improved code quality, added unit tests, and improved the performance of seeclickfix.com's public site and private municipal integrations.

Senior Developer at Evolution 1, March 2008 - August 2011

Evolution 1 sold a SaaS tool to employers to configure debit cards for their employees' FSAs and HRAs, and audit purchases made with the debit cards. I was part of the self-organized team of engineers; we practiced Scrum, wrote unit tests, and steadily improved the system architecture with object-oriented and domain-driven design in .Net technologies.

Developer at Software Impressions, May 2006 – February 2008

I mentored the team in object-oriented programming, unit testing, and refactoring, and taught them about automated builds, code generation, and domain-specific languages. We built localizable tools for companies to track ethics violations.

Developer at The Hartford, February 2002 – May 2006

I worked on the Enterprise Business Center, a portal for business insurance brokers to provide quotes from The Hartford.

Developer at Aetna Financial Services, ING Group, January 2000 - December 2001

I maintained content at aetnafinancial.com and ingafs.com.

COMMUNITY

I organized the Hartford Ruby Brigade from 2009-2010, and joined the organizing team of NewHaven.rb in 2012. In 2013 I co-founded NewHaven.io, and in 2015, as one of its board members, I participated in the first national Tech Meetup at the Whitehouse.

EDUCATION

B.S. in Computer Science, May 2006 Central Connecticut State University